<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | CompSysMed@UHH        </title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flimma</title>
      <link>/project/flimma/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/flimma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aggregating transcriptomics data across hospitals can increase sensitivity and robustness of differential expression analyses, yielding deeper clinical insights. As data exchange is often restricted by privacy legislation, meta-analyses are frequently employed to pool local results. However, if class labels are inhomogeneously distributed between cohorts, their accuracy may drop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flimma (&lt;a href=&#34;https://exbio.wzw.tum.de/flimma/&#34;&gt;https://exbio.wzw.tum.de/flimma/&lt;/a&gt;) addresses this issue by implementing the state-of-the-art workflow limma voom in a privacy-preserving manner, i.e. patient data never leaves its source site. Flimma results are identical to those generated by limma voom on combined datasets even in imbalanced scenarios where meta-analysis approaches fail.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DESMOND</title>
      <link>/project/desmond/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/desmond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Identification of differentially expressed genes is necessary for unraveling disease pathogenesis. This task is complicated by the fact that many diseases are heterogeneous at the molecular level and samples representing distinct disease subtypes may demonstrate different patterns of dysregulation. Biclustering methods are capable of identifying genes that follow a similar expression pattern only in a subset of samples and hence can consider disease heterogeneity. However, identifying biologically significant and reproducible sets of genes and samples remain challenging for the existing tools. Many recent studies have shown that the integration of gene expression and protein interaction data improves the robustness of prediction and classification and advances biomarker discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we present DESMOND, a new method for identification of Differentially ExpreSsed gene MOdules iN Diseases. DESMOND performs network-constrained biclustering on gene expression data and identifies gene modules—connected sets of genes up- or down-regulated in subsets of samples. We applied DESMOND on expression profiles of samples from two large breast cancer cohorts and have shown that the capability of DESMOND to incorporate protein interactions allows identifying the biologically meaningful gene and sample subsets and improves the reproducibility of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa1038&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa1038&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drugst.one</title>
      <link>/project/drugst.one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/drugst.one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TBD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
